<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Harsha Sista</title>
    <link>https://atsis98.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://atsis98.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 21:34:36 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://atsis98.github.io/images/icon_hu3f7b2b206f3b1a0e7569742943667eab_21402_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Italian Job</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/post/milan-thesis-tales/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 21:34:36 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://atsis98.github.io/post/milan-thesis-tales/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Harsha Sista and I shall be your journalist/protagonist in this edition of Thesis Tales. As a final year Mechanical Engineering student at BPHC, I had to dedicate a semester to pursue either the Practice School II program or switch to a thesis. Cultivating an inclination towards the world of research through my second and third year of college, I decided that it would benefit my future if I pursued a thesis and got a taste of how life in the world of academia would be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve had an affinity for outer space and flying objects since childhood, and I aimed to convert that into a tangible career path during the course of my undergraduate studies. From taking up courses, both online and on-campus to further my understanding to being a part of various technical teams, I attempted to mould my profile to become proficient with fluid mechanics and dynamics. Hoping to work in Aerodynamics or Computational Fluid Dynamics, I started looking up about various professors at prestigious institutions across the globe who worked in these fields, going by their research impact and the research output of the universities they worked in. After creating a shortlist, I started sending out mails in January 2019, which was rather late in hindsight. I mailed around 170 professors, out of which I received around 30 rejections. Towards the end of February, I finally got an acceptance from Prof. Luigi Vigevano at the Department of Aerospace Engineering, Politecnico di Milano (Polimi). I was elated at the prospect of going to an institute ranked #7 by QS in the field of Aerospace Engineering, and began the formalities of the PS to Thesis conversion and my Visa Application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never having been out of the country – going to Milan promised to be an eye-opening experience. In addition to hosting one of the premier research institutes in the world, Milan is also a cultural epicentre, which appealed to my interests. August is the summer month in Italy, during which most colleges have holidays. Polimi was scheduled to remain shut for an entire week, so I planned a small trip across the beautiful land of Italy at that time. Hopping from Rome to Venice, while visiting Florence, Pisa and the coastal Villages of Cinque Terre, the week-long trip provided memories for a lifetime. In addition, Milan houses the San Siro, the shared football stadium of AC Milan and Internazionale, and is home to the Monza Formula 1 track as well. Being an avid fan of both sports, I attended three Champions League matches and the 2019 Italian Grand Prix at Monza, fulfilling a lifelong dream of being present at a live sporting event. Even if you disregard these high-profile sporting attractions, Milan as a city can be described as a crossroad where the classics and the modern meet. It is truly a wonderfully vibrant city, ensuring that the time I got off my thesis was well spent exploring the city on foot and through the immaculate public transportation system.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-attending-the-2019-italian-grand-prix-at-monza&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/milan-thesis-tales/f1_huacd3cdee22a58d6b5c15a20398f3c132_2437041_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;4000&#34; height=&#34;1824&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Attending the 2019 Italian Grand Prix at Monza
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked at Polimi from mid-July to the end of December, a duration of 5 and a half months. My work involved running simulations on their in-house software called ROSITA and investigating the aerodynamic and aeroacoustic features of rotating helicopter blades. I worked directly with Prof. Vigevano, with Jinbin Fu, a PhD student, occasionally helping me out. Although I knew the principles of aerodynamics, aeroacoustics was a new field for me, and operating the Linux terminal to tweak the software and run simulations taught me a lot. It took a bit of time to get used to the new environment and the task expected of me, with most of July and August going in familiarizing myself with the software and the concepts required for me to run the simulations. Prof. Vigevano was immensely helpful in this process, and once I was confident enough, the simulations and analysis of results were familiar territories.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-rotorcraft-aerodynamic-laboratory&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/milan-thesis-tales/laboratory_hud0fc019a3a7022fc27409f09ec96511a_2300065_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;750&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The Rotorcraft Aerodynamic Laboratory
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of funding, I could not receive any funding from BITS. After consultations with Prof. Vigevano, it was decided that I would not be required to pay any fee to Polimi, although there would be no funds to support my stay in Milan. While this seemed a costly endeavour, I believe it was worth every rupee, for the enormity of the opportunity and the plethora of avenues it opened for me.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-prof-vigevano-and-me&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/milan-thesis-tales/featured_hu9302c3ae5e5b798b54a320e47a322ef8_1488670_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Prof. Vigevano and me
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people ask me about the benefit of doing an off-campus thesis abroad. I would say that it boils down to two parameters: international research exposure and an opportunity to make an informed decision about your future. The research environment is very different abroad, as compared to India. While our curriculum focuses on bookish learning with provisions to gain hands-on experience, learning among peers and meaningful academic interactions with Professors are two things which I feel are underrepresented in the Indian College Education system. While BITS follows a modern approach with a flexible curriculum and a competent peer group, I feel that the system is open enough to incorporate both of the above aspects to help us learn better. Apart from that, the facilities I found at Polimi were cutting-edge in most respects, providing a perfect base for academic research to take flight. Regarding my point about making an informed decision, the thesis gave me a glimpse into my future, teaching me the appropriate research methodology and the avenues to be explored in academia. This experience converted my initial feeling of going for masters and ultimately, a PhD into a clearer idea of pursuing a PhD in a subfield of Aerodynamics. This process of gaining clarity is crucial in deciding your academic future, as a hasty decision at this juncture might lead to unfavourable consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another question I get a lot is the importance of CGPA while applying for a thesis and the importance given to your profile apart from the all-important number. In my experience, both personal and anecdotal, I have observed that you will have a higher chance of getting accepted if you have previous research experience in the field you are applying to. In general, having a low CGPA requires you to have something that offsets and explains it. In my case, it was my projects and my involvement in the technical teams, but there is no set rubric for the same. All I can say is that you can never be sure of what a Professor is looking for, so strive to be the best version of yourself and don’t estimate the worth of your profile based only on your CGPA.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I believe it can fly</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/post/airplane/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 19:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://atsis98.github.io/post/airplane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The miracle of flight has astounded humans for centuries. Since the dawn of time, there have been stories, myths, and legends talking about mankind’s attempt to mimic the action of birds and make the skies his own. From the winged Pegasus overthrowing monsters on the battlefield to the tragic tale of Icarus - the man who flew too high, these stories perhaps reflect the failed attempts made by the ancients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we may not know much about the distant past, the journey to flight has had many key moments from the middle ages: Leonardo da Vinci’s schematics that were ahead of their time, the Montgolfier brothers taking to the skies aboard a hot air balloon and the various gliders that were designed by George Cayley and Otto Lilienthal. However, the moment that history has immortalized is the daring hop across 120 feet that the engine-powered contraption that the Wright brothers fabricated at Kitty Hawk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that 1903 breakthrough, the concept of flight took off, reaching greater heights and capturing the imagination of the public. Lindbergh and Amelia Earhart’s trans-Atlantic flights, the development of military aircraft for the World Wars and the development of aviation giants post-WW II have in a few short years brought the impossible to the common man. Now, you might be wondering why I am giving you a lesson in the history of flight; I am doing so to give an insight into why I am inspired by the phenomenon, and how that came to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve always been a voracious reader, ever since I learned how to, at a very young age. Although I loved stories, the books that fascinated me the most were the Young Scientist and Childcraft book series, which was aimed to give kids an introduction to the world of science and technology. I found myself drawn towards the books that talked about space exploration and the way humans defied the gravity of the Earth to quite literally, reach for the stars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As that childhood dream matured into adolescence, I started to think in terms of choosing a career that would have me working towards my passion, taking up a science stream in high school. I was in Class 11 when we had someone come and teach us how to make a plane with balsa wood as part of our school ‘Cultural Week”. That was where I first got the opportunity to convert a dream into a tangible reality. We used the energy stored in a twisted rubber band to rotate the rudimentary propeller and had a competition to see whose plane would be the most stable and fly the farthest.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-balsa-plane-i-left-built-with-the-help-of-my-classmates&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/airplane/Balsa_hu601d16702d14b37cc2e74d2d7f41670a_102313_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The balsa plane I (left) built with the help of my classmates
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After graduating from school, I took up Mechanical Engineering as my undergraduate major at BITS Pilani, Hyderabad Campus, the top-ranked private university in India. I took part in various competitions and extracurricular activities, building my skill-set and learning as much as I could. In my fourth semester, we were required to design something for the Production Techniques course and spend the next semester fabricating it using some techniques taught in the course. By this time, I had learned the basics of flight theory from online courses and had an understanding of how an object heavier than air could fly.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-four-basic-forces-experienced-by-an-airplane&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/airplane/featured_hu6b2d4c0d1c8c130b9ed638ecabb5c823_4058_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpeg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;350&#34; height=&#34;144&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The four basic forces experienced by an airplane
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this was a group project, my friends and I decided to try our hands at designing a full-fledged airplane. It was quite different from what everyone else was doing, but we were determined to give it a go. The objectives we came up with for the project are summarized below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To design a full CAD model of an aircraft.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To fabricate the CAD model in parts, using 3-D printing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To move the control surfaces using servo motors and rotate the propeller using an electric motor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To make a deployable landing gear mechanism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We planned to manufacture each part individually using the 3D printer on campus. Considering the size of the parts and the 3D printer dimensions, the bigger parts like fuselage and wings had to be cut into 2-4 parts as per the requirements. Unfortunately, due to the dimensional restrictions of the 3D printer and a delay in procuring the materials, we were only able to fabricate a small prototype of the design, and not make the full-fledged scaled version we planned to make. Therefore, the objective about the movable control surfaces did not come to fruition either.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-3d-printed-prototype-we-were-able-to-fabricate&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/airplane/project_hu27f7dc34c9db8fd2b063f3fba6be9864_95539_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The 3D printed prototype we were able to fabricate
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experience taught us a valuable lesson, that translating an idea to a finished product takes a lot of effort, and there will be obstacles that we might not anticipate in the way. Since then, I have taken up various other electives and projects that have convinced me of my desire for pursuing higher studies and shaped my research acumen, but I certainly hope that I will get a chance to work on airplanes in the future, and maybe even build a functional one someday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A day in the life of a NALCO intern</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/post/ps1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 16:00:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://atsis98.github.io/post/ps1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The article chronicles a typical day during my internship at the National Aluminium Company, Mines and Refinery Complex, at Damanjodi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alarm rings. I reach to my side and turn it off. Somewhere, my subconscious self tells me to get up and wash those clothes lying in my bag, but my sleepy mind tunes it out and decides to wait for the next alarm by sleeping again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7:10 am – the dutiful alarm rings once again. I open my eyes, turn it off again, not realizing that it is the last of the three alarms I set. My eyes close, and when they open again, a sudden panic sets in on me, I turn to look at my phone, and see that it’s 7:35.
I jolt awake, and drop my phone in the process. Perfect. I just hope it’s not broken. The moment of trepidation passes as I see that it&amp;rsquo;s safe. I scramble into the bathroom to brush and take a bath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let me give you a little context as to why waking up at 7:35 is a disaster. My PS station is at National Aluminium Company, Refinery and Mines Complex, Damanjodi. The working hours are 8 to 5, six days a week, and the 17 of us from all three campuses of BITS are trainees for the summer.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-entrance-to-the-nalco-plant&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/ps1/featured_hu7aaa47139f96ab22601c15ecad4efb91_3849188_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;4640&#34; height=&#34;3480&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The entrance to the NALCO Plant
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you a little bit about the plant as well. Its primary purpose is to obtain alumina from the raw Bauxite, so that it can be sent to the other plant in Angul to obtain aluminium. So, the entire refinery uses various techniques to produce Alumina through a process called Bayer’s Process.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-a-view-of-the-steam-and-power-plant&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/ps1/plant_hudc4f73c1894fad3f9a565eae014f3af0_4566895_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;3480&#34; height=&#34;4640&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A view of the Steam and Power Plant
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, coming back to today, I rushed to get ready by 8. Got there by 8:10, hurriedly woke my roommates and waited for them to get ready as well. By the time we got ready, called an auto and reached the gate, it was 9:20. After a little drama at the gate for being late, we went to have breakfast at the canteen and then went to our respective departments.
I had been allotted the Steam and Power Plant (SPP), which served the double purpose of generating steam to be used in the process and generating electricity as a by-product. I went to meet my mentor, and he sat me down and explained how a boiler works. Since I have only completed my second year, I have a very limited knowledge of things that concern the plant, and whatever I’ve been learning here is almost entirely new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I listened to him with a combination of fascination and boredom, and when he had finished with the basic outline, he sent me to the boiler control room to visit the actual thing. A site engineer showed me around the place, explaining how things worked while showing me the different components and connections that worked perfectly in harmony to produce the desired results. I will not go into the technical details, partly because I don’t know them completely, but mostly because I wouldn’t want you getting bored by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the site visit, I went back to my mentor’s office. My days till now had mostly consisted of him teaching me things that I would learn in my third year, and their practical applications. I soon got used to the routine, and have begun to learn quite a few things, which I’m sure will help me in my studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went back around 11:30, and the two of us discussed how water was converted to steam and then superheated, through the boiler and its accessories. Although it sounds like a simple process, there is more to it than meets the eye. Every little detail has to be taken care of, every parameter scrutinized, if the entire apparatus has to function as per requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He told me to study about boiler auxiliaries and mountings. Usually, he asks me to come back in the afternoon for another site visit, but today was different. He told me that without at least a basic knowledge of what’s going on in the system, a site visit would not be beneficial. He therefore let me go back to hostel at 1, telling me to come prepared tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I walked the 3 kilometres to the main gate, elated at the half-day and got into an auto that took me back to my hostel. Another day gone, where I learnt a little, experienced a new marvel of engineering, satisfied a little bit of my curiosity, and got an unexpected let off as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good day indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
