<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Harsha Sista</title>
    <link>https://atsis98.github.io/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://atsis98.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 22:38:08 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://atsis98.github.io/images/icon_hu3f7b2b206f3b1a0e7569742943667eab_21402_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Simulations and Design of a Novel Laparoscopic Instrument </title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/project/laparoscopy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 22:38:08 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://atsis98.github.io/project/laparoscopy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The project aims to introduce a new design of an instrument that combines the functionality of surgical forceps, a Suction-Irrigation (S-I) device, and a Carbon Dioxide (CO2) insufflator. To understand the project in the right context, I will start with a brief introduction to surgery and laparoscopy before moving on to the details of the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bintroductionb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Introduction&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abdominal cavity has long been a focus for surgical procedures since it contains a variety of organs and is relatively easy to access from the outside. However, surgeons traditionally made a cut that was 6-12 inches long to see the organ they were working on and give enough room for the proper maneuvers. However, the onset of laparoscopy changed this completely. Laparoscopy is a minimally-invasive diagnostic procedure used by surgeons to examine and operate upon organs in the abdomen. Several small cuts are made, usually less than half an inch wide, through which a camera and the surgical instruments are inserted. This advantages of doing so are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is minimal scarring since the size of the cuts is smaller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lesser possibility of hemorrhaging, leading to the lesser necessity of blood transfusions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lesser pain for the patient&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faster recovery time, leading to quicker normalization back into society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to these advantages, laparoscopy has quickly gained traction among the medical community as a viable alternative to opening up the abdominal cavity.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-1-an-example-of-laparoscopy&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/laparoscopy/featured_hu26bf59bc12cb55b847555cdae4283cbf_138972_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;384&#34; height=&#34;412&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 1: An example of laparoscopy
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bhow-is-laparoscopic-surgery-performedb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;How is Laparoscopic Surgery performed?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In laparoscopic surgery, the surgeon views the abdominal cavity from the monitor and operates by creating multiple incisions and inserting trocars of 5-12 mm sizes, as shown in the figure below. A trocar is a surgical instrument that is sharp-pointed and is used with the cannula to puncture the abdominal cavity and to insert different instruments through it.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-2-an-overview-of-the-instruments-used-in-a-laparoscopic-surgery&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/laparoscopy/Figure%202_hu21d4ab8a7c117cd6dd53b1a6e609b581_39065_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;331&#34; height=&#34;230&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 2: An overview of the instruments used in a laparoscopic surgery
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, the surgeon makes a small incision through a trocar near the belly button. Then a camera-enabled laparoscope is inserted into the abdominal cavity through a trocar into the first of the three ports. The abdomen is inflated with carbon dioxide gas (a method known as pneumoperitoneum) through the second port to view internal organs clearly on a monitor. The reason for preferring carbon dioxide over other gases is that it is non-flammable, non-combustible, colorless, readily soluble in water, cheap, and reduces the risk of complications occurring by blood clots in veins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final port is for the laparoscopic forceps, to perform operations such as grasping, cutting, lasing, cauterizing, etc. After inflating the carbon dioxide gas, the surgeon inserts the required instruments and begins operating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bwhat-is-being-done-in-the-projectb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;What is being done in the project?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objectives of the project are enumerated below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To design and develop a laparoscopic surgical device which:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Functions as a multipurpose and reusable instrument that can cut, grasp, and cauterize the tissue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is useful for simultaneous suction and irrigation and Carbon dioxide insufflation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provides added safety by avoiding multiple insertion and removal, reducing the time of surgery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can be assembled and disassembled with ease, facilitating fast sterilization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To simulate the flow of blood through the annular region in ANSYS Fluent using the various models of non-newtonian flow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To simulate the multiphase flow of carbon dioxide and water for various volume fractions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bpart-1-designing-the-novel-instrumentb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Part 1: Designing the novel instrument&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined the ongoing project in January 2020, with the initial objective of running simulations, but with my previous experience with design and Solidworks in particular, I started on converting the conceptual idea into a tangible design. The idea was simple, modify and add on to an existing design of the forceps, as shown in the figure below:&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-3-existing-surgical-forceps&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/laparoscopy/Figure%203_hu73be1a776e2f31dc7b2e46a21dc8499b_194555_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 3: Existing surgical forceps
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve the desired multi-functionality, we decided to add a sleeve covering the forceps, which would act as the common conduit for the S-I process as well as the CO2 insufflation, depending on usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After spending the first few weeks building a forceps assembly based on existing designs, I added the outer sleeve and other components as required. The design process was iterative in nature, with me working closely with my two advising professors and the Ph.D. student to give it the desired shape, literally and figuratively. After all the requirements were met, we filed an Invention Disclosure Form and applied for an Indian Patent for our design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bpart-2-non-newtonian-simulationsb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Part 2: Non-Newtonian Simulations&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is a non-Newtonian fluid? It is a fluid that does not follow Newton&amp;rsquo;s law of viscosity. Now, what is that? Newton defines viscosity as the ratio between shear stress and shear rate.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure &gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/laparoscopy/Figure%204_hu53bea492d808f37091dd0162a401dc57_9140_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;320&#34; height=&#34;56&#34;&gt;




&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Newtonian fluids, the viscosity remains constant and is independent of stress. In non-Newtonian fluids, viscosity can change when under force to either more liquid or more solid, so they can become thicker or thinner under force. An example of this is ketchup becoming runnier when shaken (and possibly even stirred).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blood is one such non-newtonian fluid. Since laparoscopic surgery involves grasping tissue using forceps and using the S-I apparatus to suck out the excess fluids, blood is the obvious choice for the fluid to simulate for our instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many models available to model blood as a non-newtonian fluid in ANSYS, a simulation software. We chose to go with two such models and run simulations to decide which gave better results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the outer sleeve was added onto the design, I extracted a fluid domain from it, which would serve as the geometry for all the fluid simulations we were going to do. Importing it into ANSYS, we spent a couple of weeks conducting mesh-independent studies to select one final mesh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, with the two models and the final mesh, we simulated the process of the apparatus sucking the blood out of the operating area, by giving the appropriate pressure differences. The resulting depictions of the flow physics were interesting, to say the least, and make up the crux of a couple of research papers that are being written right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bpart-3-multiphase-simulationsb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Part 3: Multiphase Simulations&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The part I am currently working on, apart from writing a few papers detailing our research, is multiphase simulations. So what exactly does multiphase flow mean? It refers to the flow of two or more fluid phases through the same medium. In this case, for CO2 insufflation, CO2 and air make up the two phases that flow through the outer sleeve.
Therefore, the modeling of this situation on ANSYS is much more complex. To reduce a degree of complexity, the inlet was divided into two fractions, according to the respective volume fraction of the two elements, and then simulated in Fluent. These are very computationally intensive simulations, which in ordinary speak means that they take a lot of time. For the next month or so, I will be working on this. Stay tuned for further updates, and you just might be rewarded with more details for your patience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bconclusionb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been working on this project since the beginning of the year. Although this is a new area of research, having never ventured to the biomechanical side of my degree, it caught my interest in my initial conversations with Prof. Murthy when I approached him for a project back in November last year. Although most of my research work has been related to topics that come under the banner of Aerospace Engineering, I am glad I took up a topic that was on a different segment of the broad Mechanical umbrella.
In addition to giving me insights into the design and simulation of a practical problem, this project honed my research methodology, especially with respect to the iterative nature of the process and the hard work involved in sowing the seeds that will eventually blossom into tangible branches of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am deeply grateful to have the opportunity to have worked for an extended period of time on this project, and I believe that my skillset is much improved because of this. Carrying this forward, I shall complete the rest of my tenure with the same enthusiasm for learning with which I began this journey.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aerodynamic Study of the flow field around the Tail Rotor and Fuselage of a Rotorcraft.</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 23:58:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this thesis, the aerodynamic study of the flow field around the tail rotor and fuselage of a rotorcraft is conducted by generating a high-resolution grid using ANSYS ICEM. Subsequent simulations are carried out on the in-house CFD solver, ROSITA, using the Navier-Stokes governing equation in combination with the Spallart-Allmaras Turbulence Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bintroductionb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Introduction&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aerodynamics has always been at the cutting edge with respect to the development of aircraft and rotorcraft. With the development of computational methods and the resource to put them to use, aerodynamics has grown into something bigger and better. With today’s technology and tools, it is possible to analyze the flow past a stationary wing or a moving rotor and improve the design according to the requirements accordingly. Consequently, a lot of research has focused on this sector of the aerospace industry. With rotorcraft being more inherently complex aeromechanical vehicles, the understanding of the development of the flow field around them has lagged behind the traditional fixed-wing planes. Studying how the flow interacts and the noise it generates is garnering more attention as people are looking to increase the efficiency of future machines in terms of performance, as well as the generated sound. Therefore, gaining an understanding of noise generation and its relation to the aerodynamics of rotorcraft is of the utmost importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bcontext-of-the-present-workb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Context of the present work&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scientific work undertaken during the course of this project is in the context of the work done by the European Action Group AG 24, ‘Helicopter Fuselage Scattering Effects for Exterior/Interior Noise Reduction’ in the Group for Aeronautical Research and Technology in Europe (GARTEUR). The objectives of this AG are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To develop and validate numerical prediction methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To generate a unique noise scattering database through wind tunnel tests using generic configurations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bobjectivesb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objectives of my thesis were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grid generation around the tail rotor and the fuselage used by the Group for Aeronautical Research and Technology in Europe (GARTEUR) for the study of scattering by the helicopter fuselage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usage of the in-house solver, Rotorcraft Solver Italy (ROSITA), to run aerodynamic simulations on the isolated tail rotor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding the basics of aeroacoustics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running the simulation on the Rotor plus Fuselage Configuration on ROSITA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ban-insight-into-noiseb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;An insight into Noise&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noise can be generated from rotorcraft from a variety of sources, out of which the rotor, the engine, and the transmission, are the major sources. In the previous two decades, noise reduction has received industrial attention due to certification rules becoming more stringent. Due to industrial involvement, the development of prediction codes has taken a turn for the better. To meet the needs of the industry, the research into noise reduction has really taken off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noise is broadly classified into three categories, as shown in Figure 1:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;loading and broadband noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blade-vortex noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;thickness and high-speed impulsive noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-1-different-kinds-of-noise-generated-by-a-helicopter-rotor&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/Fig.1_hu0c2932c643e9621c1149e8bdfdc1fa74_78611_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;600&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 1: Different kinds of noise generated by a Helicopter Rotor.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A helicopter rotor is essentially an unsteady mechanism due to the velocity difference between the advancing and retreating sides. As shown in Figure 2, this creates different kinds of impacts and wakes, leading to noise generation.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-2-a-schematic-of-the-aeromechanical-environment-of-a-helicopter-rotor&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/featured_hufae70a7c83ace065abfe7f91d4a16909_114735_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;674&#34; height=&#34;407&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 2: A schematic of the aeromechanical environment of a helicopter rotor.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prediction codes are used to simulate the noise generated by helicopters and are divided into the following two categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computational Aeroacoustics Approach (CAA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Approach based on Integral formulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While CAA permits a combined aerodynamic and aeroacoustic study, it is very computationally intensive, since it is based on the classical field methods. On the other hand, Integral methods have a pre-requisite of the aerodynamic knowledge around the rotor but are more suitable for obtaining aeroacoustic data at any point in the given field. It is in the development of such integral methods that the current research trend has its focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bgeometry-and-meshingb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Geometry and meshing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The geometry used by AG24 is that of a simple fuselage, with a tail boom and a tail rotor. Since the focus of this project was only on the tail rotor, only the relevant parts were extracted, as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-3-blade-and-hub-assembly-with-part-of-the-drive-shaft&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/Fig.3_hu5be18ae7203f080ede98b2293bd41ce7_29327_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 3: Blade and Hub assembly, with part of the drive shaft
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For simplification of the simulation process, the hub and the drive shaft of the assembly are neglected during calculations, and the resultant geometry is depicted below:&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-4-only-the-blades&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/Fig.4_hu2ef0ed3b2f81acd20a1b5dffaafac1c7_6959_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 4: Only the Blades
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high-resolution grid around the rotor is required for the computation of the aerodynamics around the specified geometry for achieving a mesh independent simulation. During the solving process, the mesh should also be able to tag onto another background mesh if necessary. Due to the flexibility, it offers during meshing and the variety of options it provides for meshing complex and faceted geometries, ANSYS ICEM has been used as the meshing software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bsimulation-setupb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Simulation setup&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ROtorcraft Software ITAly (ROSITA), version V 4.63, is the in-house solver that is used for this simulation during the course of this thesis. Its core element is a multi-block-structured steady, or unsteady solver with a second-order discretization scheme that supports overset grids. It supports the usage of the Chimera method, also known as the overset mesh technique, for meshing the domain. The overset method has multiple meshes with different geometrical complexities and tag them to a single overarching mesh. In this scenario, the surface mesh is tagged to the background mesh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methodology to be followed for running the simulation is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up parameters like the Governing Equations, Turbulence model, and time step in the configuration file, ROSITA.cfg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assigning the number of processors required for computation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Executing the code and running the post-processor after completion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ROSITA offers a variety of options for the solution: Solving the Euler equations, solving the Navier-Stokes equations without any turbulence model, and solving the RANS equations with a Spallart-Allmaras (S-A) turbulence model. To make a comparative study, the Blade Rotor simulation was run with two different setups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navier-Stokes equation without turbulence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navier-Stokes equation with Spallart-Allmaras turbulence model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bresult-extraction-on-tecolotb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Result extraction on Tecolot&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tecplot is a data visualization and post-processing software that is suitable for working with raw simulation data. Since the ROSITA post-processor outputs files in a Tecplot format, it is the natural choice for analyzing the results of the simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distribution of pressure over the surface of the blade is an interesting phenomenon that calls to be investigated. It is also important from an aeroacoustic point of view since many noise propagation codes, and studies use the pressure field in their calculations. Therefore, obtaining a proper pressure distribution is essential, and a comparison to see which model yields the better results is made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ROSITA Solver generates two surface files in the .plt format, with data for each of the two blades. Combining the two files in Tecplot, we get the following image:&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-5-surface-pressure-contours-on-both-blades&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/Fig.5_hubed5b54afa66e2327a57c91e6472468d_17528_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 5: Surface pressure contours on both blades
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pressure contours are nearly symmetrical in the opposite direction and consistent with what is expected of a rotating blade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The behavior of the Mach Number provides proper insight into the aerodynamics of the flow field surrounding the rotor blade. Unlike pressure, it is not directly useful from an aeroacoustic point of view, but the implications in Aerodynamics are useful enough to study it in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bconclusionb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flow development around the tail rotor of the helicopter is mostly as expected, with a separation observed at the leading edge and a region of recirculation observed as the distance from the hub increases along the span of the blade. The observations made from the results can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The oscillation in the solution is much lesser in the Turbulence Model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With an increase in y, the distance span-wise from the hub, the Mach Number as well as the flow separation increase, as expected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The difference in plots between the two cases is tangible, as the separation region is better defined with the turbulence model. This is because the S-A model specializes in solving boundary layers and adverse pressure gradients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
